These are simple objects:
هذه أشياء بسيطة:
clocks, keys, combs, glasses.
ساعات، مفاتيح، أمشاط، نظارات.
They are the things the victims of genocide in Bosnia
هذه هي الأشياء التي أخذها ضحايا التطهير العرقي في البوسنة
carried with them on their final journey.
معهم إلى مثواهم الأخير.
We are all familiar with these mundane,
كلنا نعرف هذه الأشياء العادية،
everyday objects.
التي نستعملها كل يوم.
The fact that some of the victims carried
كون بعض الضحايا قد أخذوا معهم
personal items such as toothpaste and a toothbrush
أشياء شخصية مثل معجون الأسنان وفرشاة الأسنان
is a clear sign they had no idea
يوضح كليا أنه لم تكن لديهم أدنى فكرة
what was about to happen to them.
عما كان على وشك أن يحدث لهم.
Usually, they were told that they were going to be
عادة ما يقال لهم أنه سيتم
exchanged for prisoners of war.
استبدالهم مع سجناء الحرب.
These items have been recovered
تم استرجاع هذه الأشياء
from numerous mass graves across my homeland,
من مجموعة من المقابر الجماعية في أرجاء وطني،
and as we speak, forensics are exhuming bodies
في هذه الأثناء، تقوم هيئات الطب الشرعي بالنبش
from newly discovered mass graves,
في مقابر جماعية تم اكتشافها حديثا،
20 years after the war.
بعد 20 سنة على الحرب.
And it is quite possibly the largest ever discovered.
ومن المرجح أنن تكون الأكبر التي اكتُشِفت لحد الآن.
During the four years of conflict
خلال السنوات الأربع للصراع
that devastated the Bosnian nation in the early '90s,
الذي دمر الأمة البوسنية في بداية التسعينات،
approximately 30,000 citizens, mainly civilians,
كان هناك مايقارب 30000 مواطنا، أغلبهم مدنيون،
went missing, presumed killed,
ممن فُقِدوا، أو ظُنَّ أنهم قُتِلوا،
and another 100,000 were killed
و 100000 آخرون قُتِلوا فعلا
during combat operations.
خلال العمليات الحربية.
Most of them were killed
تم قتل أغلبهم
either in the early days of the war
إما في الأيام الأولى للحرب
or towards the end of the hostilities,
أو في نهاية الأعمال العدائية،
when U.N. safe zones like Srebrenica
حين وقعت المناطق الآمنة التابعة للأمم المتحدة مثل سريبرينيتشا
fell into the hands of the Serb army.
في يد الجيش الصربي.
The international criminal tribunal
أصدرت محكمة الجرائم الدولية
delivered a number of sentences
عددا من الأحكام
for crimes against humanity and genocide.
بخصوص الجرائم ضد الإنسانية والتطهير العرقي.
Genocide is a systematic and deliberate
التطهير العرقي هو تدمير متعمد ومنظم
destruction of a racial, political, religious
لمجموعة سياسية أو دينية
or ethnic group.
أو عرقية.
As much as genocide is about killing.
بقدر ما يتعلق التطهير العرقي بالقتل،
It is also about destroying their property,
فهو أيضا متعلق بتدمير ممتلكاتهم
their cultural heritage,
وميراثهم الثقافي،
and ultimately the very notion that they ever existed.
وفي نهاية المطاف تدمير الفكرة العميقة أنهم وُجِدوا أصلا.
Genocide is not only about the killing;
لا يتعلق التطهير العرقي بالقتل فقط؛
it is about the denied identity.
بل بنفي الهوية.
There are always traces —
هناك دائما دلائل--
no such thing as a perfect crime.
لا توجد جريمة مثالية.
There are always remnants of the perished ones
هناك دائما بقايا للناس الذين هلكوا
that are more durable than their fragile bodies
والتي تظل صامدة أكثر من أجسادهم الهشة
and our selective and fading memory of them.
ومن ذاكرتنا الانتقائية المتلاشية عنهم.
These items are recovered
تم استرجاع هذه الأشياء
from numerous mass graves,
من العديد من المقابر الجماعية،
and the main goal of this collection of the items
والهدف الأساسي من جمع هذه الأشياء
is a unique process
هو عملية فريدة
of identifying those who disappeared in the killings,
للتعرف على من اختفى في عمليات القتل،
the first act of genocide on European soil
أول عملية تطهير عرقي على التراب الأوروبي
since the Holocaust.
منذ الهولوكوست.
Not a single body should remain undiscovered
ليس على أي من هذه الأجساد أن تظل غير مكتشفة
or unidentified.
أو غير معرفة.
Once recovered,
حالما يتم استعادتها
these items that the victims carried with them
يتم تنظيف وتحليل هذه الأشياء التي حملها الضحايا معهم
on their way to execution
في طريقهم إلى الإعدام
are carefully cleaned, analyzed,
بعناية فائقة،
catalogued and stored.
ويتم فهرستها وتخزينها.
Thousands of artifacts are packed in white plastic bags
تم تعبئة الآلاف من التحف في أكياس بلاستيكية
just like the ones you see on CSI.
مثل التي ترونها في سلسلة CSI .
These objects are used as a forensic tool
تُستَعمل هذه الأشياء كأداة للطب الشرعي
in visual identification of the victims,
للتعرف بصريا على هوية الضحايا،
but they are also used as very valuable forensic evidence
لكنها تستعمل أيضا كأدلة شرعية قيمة
in the ongoing war crimes trials.
في محاكمات الجرائم الحربية الجارية.
Survivors are occasionally called
يتم استدعاء الناجين أحيانا
to try to identify these items physically,
لمحاولة التعرف على هذه الأشياء شخصيا،
but physical browsing is extremely difficult,
لكن التصفح الشخصي مضن للغاية،
an ineffective and painful process.
وهي عملية مؤلمة وغير مجدية.
Once the forensics and doctors and lawyers
حالما ينتهي الأطباء الشرعيون والأطباء والمحامون
are done with these objects,
من هذه الأشياء،
they become orphans of the narrative.
فإنها تصبح حبيسة السرد.
Many of them get destroyed, believe it or not,
يتم التخلص من العديد منها، صدق أولا تصدق،
or they get simply shelved,
أو يتم وضعها ببساطة على الرف
out of sight and out of mind.
بعيدة عن الأنظار وعن العقول.
I decided a few years ago
قررت منذ بضع سنوات
to photograph every single exhumed item
أن أصور كل شيء مستخرج
in order to create a visual archive
بهدف خلق أرشيف بصري
that survivors could easily browse.
ليتمكن الناجون من تصفحه بسهولة.
As a storyteller, I like to give back to the community.
كراو للقصة، أريد أن أرد الجميل للمجتمع.
I like to move beyond raising awareness.
أريد أن أتحرك إلى ما وراء رفع مستوى الوعي.
And in this case, someone may
في هذه الحالة، يمكن لأحدهم
recognize these items
أن يتعرف على هذه الأشياء
or at least their photographs will remain
أو على الأقل ستظل هذه الصور
as a permanent, unbiased and accurate reminder
كمذكر دائم، غير منحاز ودقيق
of what happened.
لما جرى.
Photography is about empathy,
التصوير متعلق بالتعاطف،
and the familiarity of these items guarantee empathy.
والألفة التي تعطيها هذه الأشياء ستضمن هذا التعاطف.
In this case, I am merely a tool,
في هذه الحالة، أنا بالكاد أكون أداة،
a forensic, if you like,
طبيبا شرعيا، إن راق لكم هذا.
and the result is a photography that is as close
والنتيجة أن التصوير يكون أقرب
as possible of being a document.
ما يكون إلى وثيقة.
Once all the missing persons are identified,
حالما يتم التعرف على كل الناس المفقودين،
only decaying bodies in their graves
وحدها الجثث المتحللة في القبور
and these everyday items will remain.
وهذه الأشياء العادية سوف تبقى.
In all their simplicity,
بكل بساطتها،
these items are the last testament
هذه الأشياء هي الشهادة الأخيرة
to the identity of the victims,
للتعرف على هوية الضحايا،
the last permanent reminder
هي التذكير الأخير الباقي
that these people ever existed.
عن أن هؤلاء قد عاشوا بالأصل.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)